<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-17T04:35:53+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">凪良ゆう「滅びの前のシャングリラ」</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2025/horobi-no-mae-no/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="凪良ゆう「滅びの前のシャングリラ」"/><published>2025-01-11T16:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-11T16:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2025/horobi-no-mae-no</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2025/horobi-no-mae-no/"><![CDATA[<p>もうすぐ世界が滅びる。そんな恐ろしい状況下では、法も礼儀も世間体も脆く崩れ、飲食料や生活用品の窃盗のし合い、そして時に殺し合いが繰り広げられる。しかし、凪良ゆう著「滅びの前のシャングリラ」（中央公論新社、2020）では、恐ろしい物語が描かれているのかというと、そうではない。</p> <p>凪良ゆうの描く世界の終わりには、殺し・騙し・窃盗・飢えなどももちろん登場する。しかし、それよりも遥かに力を持って、鮮やかに飛び出してくるのは、世界が終わるからこそ見つけることのできた小さな幸せの数々である。破滅へのレールを止めることなく走り続ける世界は、まるで放火された火薬倉庫のように、これまでにないほど色とりどりの美しい火花を散らしながら破滅へと転がり進んでゆく。</p> <p>「滅びの前のシャングリラ」の中でまず否応なしに突きつけられるのが、厳しい状況下における犠牲の必然性である。「自分や自分の愛する人の命を守るためなら、他の人を犠牲にするか？」それは、必要に迫られないならば、できれば考えたくさえないような問いである。シングルマザーとして苦境を乗り越えてきた元ヤンの母、江那静香は、我が子を眺めこう思う。</p> <blockquote> あたしは絶対に子供たちを飢えさせないと誓っていた。世界がこうなる前から、そう決めて生きてきた。けれど我が子を守りたいと願うほど、それ以外を切り捨てる選択を強いられる。 </blockquote> <p>今までの世界では、子供を飢えさせないためには、自分が身を削って働けばよかった。しかし無秩序の世界では、我が子を守ることは、他の子供を犠牲にすることにもなりかねないのだ。究極の状況下では、揺るぎないと思っていた倫理観も、法と同じように力無く散ってゆく。しかし、それは悲しいだけのことなのだろうか。そのような静香の姿を見て、幼馴染の目力信士はこう言う。</p> <blockquote> 身勝手で逞しい、それが愛情の裏の顔ってもんだ。 </blockquote> <p>「身勝手」だけど「逞しい」。愛する人を守るためなら犠牲も厭わないその精神は、善し悪しを抜きにして、人間の心に響くものがあるのは間違いない。真っ裸の愛とでも言おうか、そこには痛々しさこその美しさがある。</p> <p>世界の終わりという状況下で初めて輝きを放ち始めるのは、むき出しの愛だけではない。静香の息子、江那友樹は、学校ではいつもいじめられっ子だった。いつもクラスメートに笑い物にされたり、使いっぱしられたり、暴力を振るわれたり、気になる女の子の前で恥をかかされたりする日々を、なんとか耐え忍んできていた。しかし彼は、世界が滅びると知ってからは、無秩序の世の中を、なんとか大切な家族と乗り切れるように様々な工夫を凝らす。生存、という大きな課題を前に、今まで学校で感じていたような、社会に組み込まれるために保たざるを得ない体裁のようなものへの圧が取っ払われる。静香が友樹に「怖くないの」と聞くと、友樹はこう答える。</p> <blockquote> 「怖いに決まってるだろう。でもこうなる前の世界より、ぼくはずっと自分が好きなんだ。前の世界は平和だったけど、いつもうっすら死にたいって思ってた。（中略）今は死にたくないって思ってるよ。でもあと十日しかない。悲しいし、怖いし、最悪だけど、それでも、ぼくはちょっといい感じに変われた気がする。あのままの世界だったら、長生きできたかもしれないけど、こんな気持ちは知らないまま死んでたかもって思う」 </blockquote> <p>命が脅かされる世の中では、様々なものが脆く散り去る。しかし、その中でこそ、自分には本当は何が（誰が）大事であったのかが明るみに出される。本当に大切なもの以外は全て洗い流されてしまった裸の世界では、命が危険に晒される代わりに、今までの平和な世界では気がつくことのできなかった幸せが、たくさん落ちているのだろう。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="japanese"/><category term="fiction"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[「身勝手で逞しい、それが愛情の裏の顔ってもんだ。」]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How To Do Nothing –Resisting the Attention Economy by Jenny Odell</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2023/how-to-do-nothing-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How To Do Nothing –Resisting the Attention Economy by Jenny Odell"/><published>2023-07-04T22:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-04T22:57:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2023/how-to-do-nothing-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2023/how-to-do-nothing-en/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m back after a long break! I first read <em>How To Do Nothing: Resisting the Attention Economy</em> by Jenny Odell in 2020 at the dawn of the pandemic. I absolutely loved it at the time, and I recently decided to re-read it. After a few chapters, I went through a thrilling realization that the impact this book had on me a few years ago was much bigger than I had recalled. I certainly remembered that I resonated with the book and took away a lot from it, but after re-reading it, I realized that this book nudged me over a shift in perspective on how I spend my own life, and many of the things I took away got baked directly into my personal goals in later years, long after I had forgotten that this book was where much of it came from.</p> <p>So what is the book about? My partner has told me that he finds the title funny because it seems that doing nothing is easy. It doesn’t require a book to tell you how! Obviously, this book is a little more than the literal title. I would summarize it as a sharp, almost academic essay on how we can regain ownership over how to spend our lives, and how we can reconnect to the world that feels increasingly disjointed.</p> <p>Odell begins the introduction with the struggle that many of us are familiar with: <em>“Nothing is harder to do than nothing. In a world where our value is determined by our productivity, many of us find our every last minute captured, optimized, or appropriated as a financial resource by the technologies that we use daily”</em>. As implied here, “nothing” in this book doesn’t quite mean literally nothing, but rather “nothing” from the point of view of the entities that financially exploit us. This not only applies to entities that exploit our time and labor, but to those that exploit our attention.</p> <p>In the first chapter, Odell discusses her personal state of crisis, following the 2016 election, that led to her necessity of doing nothing. She considers that we live in an “attention economy”, where fear, anxiety, and disruption is the oxygen for profit. I resonated strongly with her sense of being completely overwhelmed by my social media feed, which consisted of a jumbled mix of cute dogs, someone’s vacation in Greece, and breaking news about some politician doing something completely outrageous.</p> <p>In such a state of abused attention, our existence in this world becomes fragmented and start to lack context. It’s easy to <em>react</em> to what we see, but increasingly difficult to contemplate and take continued action. It’s easy to make ourselves “useful” (in a capitalistic sense) by working every possible hour, but difficult to not let the joy of life slip through our fingers. It’s easy to hit “like” on our friend’s post, but difficult to find someone to call in times of vulnerability.</p> <p>When I was experiencing a similar state of overwhelmed distress at the dawn of the pandemic, I entertained the thought of dropping everything and living in the mountains somewhere. Or more realistically (?), quitting my job and moving in with my grandma in Japan. In the second chapter, titled <em>The Impossibility of Retreat</em>, Odell discusses many examples of people attempting to retreat from the exploitative society, much like how I pictured my escape plan would look like. These examples range from the dropout movements in 1960s U.S., where people attempted to escape to the middle of nowhere to construct their own peaceful and self-contained societies, to a philosopher called Epicurus from fourth century B.C. in Ancient Greece. These attempts and their frequent failures have much to teach us about the <em>“challenges inherent in trying to extricate oneself completely from the fabric of a capitalist reality, as well as what was sometimes an ill-fated attempt to escape politics altogether”</em>.</p> <p>As a way to “resist the attention economy”, what Odell proposes in <em>How To Do Nothing</em> is not an escape from “the world”, from other people, or from politics. Instead, it is <em>“to remain in place while escaping the framework of the attention economy and an over-reliance on a filtered public opinion”</em>. In other words, Odell gives us the tools to gain back ownership of our own attention, liberating us from the captivating flashes that attempt to exploit our attention for profit 24/7.</p> <p>And how does she do that exactly? Although she introduces us to many helpful anecdotes, perspectives, and exercises, what personally spoke to me most is what she describes in her introduction as <em>“a lateral movement outward to things and people that are around us”</em>, and <em>“a movement downward into place”</em>, which then leads to her emphasis on bioregionalism. Simply put, (and perhaps overly simply put…) this can be summarized as re-connecting with the people, land, animals, and the natural environment that <em>physically</em> surrounds us. Odell tells her journey of “growing outward” and “growing downward” through several profound personal anecdotes: developing a relationship with a city-dwelling wild animal, spending time in a nearby rose garden while contemplating the history of comminuty and labor rights, and re-discovering the splendor of the natural landscape of her hometown, which up until then she considered the most boring suburb in America.</p> <p>In 2020, this book helped me realize that my mood and my whole sense of the world was so deeply affected by what I see on my little screens day to day, if not hour to hour. I would be stressed and overwhelmed trying to use every possible hour I have for “productivity”, glued to my screen while the beautiful summer sky was encapsulating the blooming flowers and people at the beach in the rich warmth. I would open Instagram for a break and get inundated with reactional political outrage, and I would truly feel like the world was falling apart, even though my day had been going perfectly well. But when I bring myself back to my immediate, physical environment, I realize that the world is NOT falling apart.</p> <p>Since 2020, I’ve been on my own journey of reconnecting with my time, place, and people. It certainly doesn’t happen overnight, and I’m still working on it every day. Funnily enough, my recent passion for learning history has helped immensely in feeling more connected with the world as well - it offers perspectives on how I fit into the world, geographically and temporally. (It also gives me comforting context that, considering the history of this country, the history of my own country, and the history of the world, I can most definitely say that the “breaking news” I’m seeing is not a catastrophe!) It’s a continuous journey, but its a one that brings me more and more joy as time passes. I’m so glad I read this book in 2020, and glad that I decided to pick it up again!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="english"/><category term="non-fiction"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A profound examination of our relationship with the world]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Historical fiction on Rikyu, the tea ceremony giant</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/rikyu-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Historical fiction on Rikyu, the tea ceremony giant"/><published>2022-12-13T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-13T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/rikyu-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/rikyu-en/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/rikyu-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/rikyu-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/rikyu-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/rikyu.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <h3 id="sen-no-rikyu-a-16th-century-man-who-moved-the-world-with-his-tea-ceremony">Sen no Rikyu: a 16th-century man who moved the world with his tea ceremony</h3> <p>Happy holidays everyone! In the midwest, the days are getting shorter and nights are getting colder. As a non-native to the midwest, I’ve always been quick to whine about the cold. Over the past couple of years, though, to my surprise, I think I’m starting to get accustomed to it! I keep myself entertained with activities like reading, cooking hearty soups, and drawing/painting.</p> <p>Today’s book is a popular Japanese historical fiction that got famous after it won some awards in Japan a few years ago. The main character is a man known as Sen no Rikyu, a name likely familiar to most everyone who grew up in Japan. He worked as a “Sado”, or a “tea ceremony leader” (for lack of better translation…), in 16th century Japan. The Japanese islands at the time, still too fragmented to be called a country, was in turmoil with numerous military clans across the islands fighting to reign at the top for nearly two hundreds of years.</p> <p>The Sado was an occupation in charge of providing the military leaders with rejuvenating tea breaks, which often included designing the tea house, decorating the rooms, preparing food, selecting rice wines, and of course, preparing the matcha green tea.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="putting-a-face-to-the-name">Putting a face to the name</h3> <p>Even though Rikyu’s name was tattooed onto my brain from childhood history classes, I knew little about what kind of person he was, or even what he actually did to become such a big name in tea ceremony. I knew he pretty much developed Japanese tea ceremony as we know it today, but honestly, what does “develop” mean in this context? Spending time with him personally for an entire book (albeit fictional, based on a true story!) really brought the Rikyu figure to life in my mind.</p> <p>Something that left a particularly strong impression was his sharp and intense obsession with beauty. His obsession appeared akin to something like an all-consuming faith - a compulsive drive that he could not let go of if he tried. Sine I thought of Japanese tea ceremony as something that’s serene, peaceful, and warm, I had subconsciously associated this kind of image with Rikyu as well, prior to reading this book. To my surprise, Rikyu in this novel is extremely pointed, stubborn, and self-confident, emitting a mysterious energy that most people can’t grasp. I really enjoyed this humanly portrait of Rikyu that I never would have guessed. In hindsight though, perhaps it naturally takes a headstrong folk like him to change history the way he did.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="a-look-into-the-sense-of-beauty-at-the-time">A look into the sense of beauty at the time</h3> <p>Another part I really enjoyed throughout this book is the glimpse into the aesthetics of the time, which is quite different from the somewhat westernized sense of beauty we have in Japan today. The aesthetics put emphasis on giving out a natural, effortless, and spontaneous sense of beauty (although the relentless pursuit of this beauty itself is often the opposite of effortlessness). It’s a stark contrast between western values, which I feel like often value unapologetically calculated order. In the novel, designs that evoke calculation were something that Rikyu hated the most. Learning such differences helped me put our current cultural values into context, as well as remind myself that what we often consider a “given” in our current society is often pretty arbitrary.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="english"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="history"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A glimpse into the historical Japanese sense of beauty]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">利休にたずねよ</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/rikyu-jp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="利休にたずねよ"/><published>2022-12-13T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-13T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/rikyu-jp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/rikyu-jp/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/rikyu-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/rikyu-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/rikyu-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/rikyu.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <h3 id="続く歴史小説愛">続く歴史小説愛</h3> <p>アメリカはすっかりクリスマス感たっぷりの季節となってきました。私の住む地域は寒さが厳しいですが、相変わらず本に身をうずめたり、あったまる料理をしたり、スケッチの勉強をしてみたりと、割と楽しく過ごしています。</p> <p>私は恐縮ながら読書に関しては割とにわか勢（？）で、趣味で本を読み始めたのもここ３年くらいです。そんなわけで、自分がどんなジャンルの本が好きかについてさえ、まだ日々学んでいるところなのですが、ビギナーなりに最近気づいたのは、歴史小説って、おもしろい！ということ。（笑）私が歴史を勉強するのが好きになり始めたのも、読書を始めたのと同じ頃だったのですが、この最高ジャンルの存在に気づくのにこんなに長くかかるとは、、、歴史大好きで小説も大好きなのに、何故か歴史は自分の中で「ノンフィクション枠」みたいなものに入っていたみたいです。以前ここにも書いた「訴訟王エジソンの標的」という本を読んで、改めて歴史小説のハズレなさに気付かされました！</p> <p>そこで手に取ったのが今回の、山本兼一さん著「利休にたずねよ」。ちょっと前に直木賞を受賞したので有名な作品です。</p> <hr/> <h3 id="歴史上の人物千利休の人間としての姿">歴史上の人物「千利休」の、人間としての姿</h3> <p>安土桃山から戦国の時代にかけて、茶の湯に人生を捧げた茶人、千利休。正直私の中でその人物像なるものは、存在しないに等しいレベルでした。「千利休」＝「茶の湯」みたいな、試験に使うだけの情報を呪文のように暗記していただけ。しかしこの読書体験を通して「利休」という人と何日間かを一緒に過ごしてみて、人間としての利休の存在が自分の中に浮かび上がり、利休自身だけでなく、その当時の時代背景への認識の解像度が一気に上がったように感じました。</p> <p>中でも色濃く印象に残ったのが、利休の、徹底的な美への執着。それは強迫観念のような、抗うことのできない神への信仰のような、恐ろしささえ覚えるようなものでした。私の今までの呪文のような歴史の理解では、茶の湯といえばなんとなく、清らかで、和やかで、温かいようなイメージ。後世に受け継がれる茶の湯を確立させた利休も、気づかずそのようなイメージと連想させてしまっていたようです。蓋を開けてみれば、利休の人間像は、（小説なので脚色があるのは承知ですが）とにかく鋭く、頑固で、自信に満ち溢れ、凡人には理解できない暗く神秘的なエネルギーを発するような存在。そんな人間くささが、読んでいてとても面白かったです。</p> <hr/> <h3 id="日本の昔の美の感覚が垣間見られる感動">日本の昔の美の感覚が垣間見られる感動</h3> <p>この小説を読んでいると、利休の追求する美意識のようなものがストーリーを通してひしひしと感じられます。そんな中で、当時の「美」に対する感覚が今とどれだけ違うものであったかも、個人的には面白いポイントでした。読んでいて連想したのは、 九鬼周造さんの著書「いきの構造」で解説されていた『いき』の定義。この本の中で著者は、日本固有の美的感覚「いき」という概念の構造について、「媚態（色気）」「意気（意気地）」そして「潔い諦め」の三つの要素があると述べています。詳しい解説は私のような人が語れるものではないので割愛しますが、小説に描かれる利休の追い求めた茶の湯の美しさには、このコンセプトとかなり通ずるところがあると感じました。生命力を感じる艶やかさ（色気）と、気品や思い切った気概（意気）のエネルギー、そして皮肉にも（？）垢抜けて執着を感じさせない、あざとくない美しさ。そんな美しさを利休は追求していたように読まれました。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="japanese"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="history"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[日本人の過去の美意識を垣間見る]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stories of Your Life and Others</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/stories-of-your-life-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stories of Your Life and Others"/><published>2022-11-26T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-26T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/stories-of-your-life-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/stories-of-your-life-en/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories-of-your-life-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories-of-your-life-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories-of-your-life-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/stories-of-your-life.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <h3 id="ted-chiang-is-a-gift-that-keeps-on-giving">Ted Chiang is a gift that keeps on giving!</h3> <p><em>Stories of Your Life and Others</em> by Ted Chiang has been on my reading list since I read his more recent work, <em>Exhalation</em>, a couple of months ago. As a person who has always been out of touch with film (and entertainment in general for that matter… yes I’m ashamed), I didn’t even know there was an award-winning film (<em>The Arrival</em>, 2016) that was based on Ted Chiang’s story until halfway through my last book!</p> <p>The verdict? This book was just as amazing as the other one! It’s safe to say that I’m now a big fan of Chiang’s. The stories can feel mind-bending at the beginning, but after a couple of pages, my mind starts flexing muscles that I didn’t know it had. Before I know it, I completely forget about the world I know and my mind wanders freely like a shapeless current.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="re-learning-the-joy-and-value-of-imagination">Re-learning the joy and value of imagination</h3> <p><em>Stories of Your Life and Others</em> is a collection of short stories that all explore many different kinds of what-if’s about the world we live in. The question “What if the world was …?” is a popular enough one that, not only has it been explored in many other sci-fi or dystopian future novels, but all of us have probably had our own such wonderings. (e.g. “What if animals could understand everything that we are saying?”)</p> <p>What stands out about Ted Chiang’s explorations of these questions is that they are incredibly creative yet grounded in realistic sharpness, and is delivered so eloquently.</p> <p>For example, one story explores a kind of cognition that is fundamentally different from the one that we humankind have. Not everyone can tackle such profound questions and deliver it so beautifully! Other examples include a story that explores what the world would look like in the presence of so-called “superhumans”, and, one of my personal favorites, one that explores what would happen if we invented a piece of technology that can remove lookism (discrimination based on one’s level of attractiveness) entirely. Would people adopt such technology? What are some new issues that would emerge? etc. etc. What makes things even more interesting is that the stage of these stories are not always set in the future, as with many sci-fi/dystopian novls, but sometimes in the middle ages or several centuries BC.</p> <p>Come to think of it, I had never put too much thought into these types of questions (“What if the world was …?”) since I entered adulthood. I was quick to shrug it off with lame responses like “Well that kind of world couldn’t possibly exist for XYZ reason”. Having read both <em>Exhalation</em> and <em>Stories of Your Life and Others</em>, I find myself opening up more and more to these imaginative explorations. Once we recognize the improbable and miraculous nature of the world that we currently live in, it’s actually not too difficult to imagine another world where the rules of the universe are entirely different. In fact, these thought experiments are not only intellectually stimulating but also offer incredibly useful insights that help us learn about ourselves.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="english"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What if the world was... different?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">短編集「あなたの人生の物語」</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/stories-of-your-life-jp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="短編集「あなたの人生の物語」"/><published>2022-11-26T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-26T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/stories-of-your-life-jp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/stories-of-your-life-jp/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories-of-your-life-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories-of-your-life-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/stories-of-your-life-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/stories-of-your-life.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <h3 id="テッドチャンの作り出す物語が面白すぎる">テッド・チャンの作り出す物語が面白すぎる</h3> <p>２〜３ヶ月前にテッド・チャン著「息吹」を読んで圧倒されて以来、同著の短編集「あなたの人生の物語」は読みたいリストに入っていました。基本的に映画やテレビに非常に疎い人間であるため知らなかったのですが、人並みに映画を見るような人たちの間では、こちらの「あなたの人生の物語」の方が、「息吹」よりも有名らしい。というのも、2016年にアカデミー賞にノミネートされたThe Arrival（邦題「メッセージ」）という大人気SF映画のベースとなっているストーリーが収録されているのが今回の本なのです。</p> <p>結論から言うと、この短編集、「息吹」にも負けないほどの、最高に面白い本でした！テッド・チャン、天才すぎる。凡人では思い付かないような設定のストーリーは、最初は何が何だかわからない状態で始まることも多いですが、数ページ読み進めるうちに、脳内の今まで使ったことのない筋肉が動き始めるような不思議な感覚に陥ります。そして、あれよあれよという間に、私の心は今自分の住んでいる世界のことをすっかり忘れ、新しい宇宙を自由に探索し始めるのです。</p> <hr/> <h3 id="自由な想像力のもたらす喜びと洞察力">自由な想像力のもたらす喜びと洞察力</h3> <p>この短編集に収録されている物語はどれも、様々な「もしも」を辿り、今私たちが住んでいる世界とはちょっと違った世界を経験させてくれます。「もしも世界が〇〇だったら、、、」という想像をしたことがある人は少なくないと思いますし、SF小説やディストピアものではこのようなテーマが頻繁に取り上げられますよね。</p> <p>テッド・チャンのすごいところは、このようなテーマを、のびのびとしたクリエイティビティで、しかし鮮明な現実性をもって、そして限りなく巧みに美しく描き出すところです。</p> <p>例えば、私たち人類が皆当たり前のように毎日使っている認知。もしもこれとは根本的に異なる認知の方式があるとすれば、それはどんなものだろうか？という模索。こんな難しい問いにじっくり向き合って、さらに読者を置いてけぼりにしないような物書きができる人なんて、そういないのではないでしょうか。他には、「いわゆる『スーパーヒューマン（超人？）』みたいなものが生まれた世界ってどんな感じになるだろう？」というような問いを探るストーリーもあれば、「もしも脳からルッキズム（外見・容姿に基づく差別）を取り除くことができる技術が生まれたら、人々はそれを取り入れるのか？どんな新たな問題が生じるだろうか？」というテーマを取り巻くストーリーも。そしてこれらの描き方が、どこまでも期待を裏切ってきて本当に面白い。SFやディストピアものでは基本的に未来が舞台にされることが多いですが、テッド・チャンの短編集では必ずしもそうではなく、中世や紀元前が舞台となるものもあったり。またフォーマットも、小説に典型的なナレーションスタイルもあれば、ドキュメンタリーのようなフォーマットで紡ぎ出されるものなど、全く隙を見せません。</p> <p>改めて考えてみると、私は大人になってから、「もしこんな世界があったら？」というような疑問に対して、「まあ、そんな世界はあり得ないから」なんてつまらない言い訳をして、あまり深く考えたことがなかったように思います。しかし、こうやって「息吹」や「あなたの人生の物語」を読むにつれて、そのような想像力あふれる問いかけに、いつのまにか心が自然と開いていきました。そもそも、今私たちの住んでいる世界がどんな魔法のような奇跡の連続で出来上がっているかに思いを馳せると、「あり得ない」と感じるような世界の存在するシナリオを思い描くのは少しも不可能ではないように思えてきます。そして、こんな「あり得ない」世界について考える思考実験のようなものって、ものすごく知的好奇心をくすぐる喜びを与えてくれるだけではなくて、自分をより深く理解する枠組みを補強してくれるなあとも感じます。例えば、「SNSが私たちに与える影響って？」なんて疑問は、あまりに自分に近すぎて一歩下がってみるのが難しかったりするけれど、「ルッキズムを取り除く技術が人に与える影響って？」という問いとなれば、完全な傍観者として騒ぎを観察することができちゃうのです。そしてそこで気づいたことが結局はSNSが私たちに与える影響についてのインサイトに繋がったりしてね。</p> <p>物語を書くことで人の心を動かせるって素敵なことですね〜。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="japanese"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[「もしも」を辿って、自分を学ぶ。]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Last Days of Night</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/last-days-of-night-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Last Days of Night"/><published>2022-10-25T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-25T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/last-days-of-night-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/last-days-of-night-en/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/last-days-of-night-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/last-days-of-night-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/last-days-of-night-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/last-days-of-night.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <h3 id="autumn-is-upon-us--time-for-some-more-books">Autumn is upon us = Time for some more books!</h3> <p>Autumn is here! I can’t help but get ecstatic at the leaves that are blooming into varying shades of yellow, orange, brown, and red. After 5 years of living in the midwest, the spring flowers and autumn leaves are growing to be my absolute favorite things about the area.</p> <p>Back home in Japan, autumn is a time when the excruciating heat and humidity of the summer slowly loosens itself to cooler, more pleasant temperatures, accompanied by lengthening nights. Many people refer to the time of the year as “reading season” perhaps for this reason. It’s a happy excuse for me to feel justified in burying myself in more books than ever :)</p> <p>Here’s one that I recently read and absolutely adored.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="historical-fiction-about-the-current-war">Historical fiction about the “current war”</h3> <p>The Last Days of Night by Graham Moore is a historical fiction based on a true story. The story is set in late-19th century Manhattan, where parts of the city is beginning to be lit by electricity rather than the longstanding gas lamps. The energy culminating from all the fear, excitement, and competition surrounding this new and otherworldly technology is palpable. No one really knows what electricity really is or how it works, including the inventors and manufacturers themselves. Despite the occasional electrocution accidents and accompanying concerns over the safety of the technology, there is no question that whoever seizes control of this technology will seize control of light itself.</p> <p>Even though Thomas Edison might have ended up the best-known name, the answer to the question “Who invented the light bulb?” is not so clear-cut. Even though Edison held the patent, he was by no means the first to come up with electrical light. Even the term “light bulb” is something entirely new at the time - raising questions such as, if someone else invented a slightly different device for electrical light, how does anyone determine if this infringes on Edison’s “light bulb”?</p> <p>The Last Days of Night paints the legal, technological, and business battles between two of the strongest electric companies in the world, Westinghouse Electric and Edison’s General Electric, now referred to by historians as the “current war”.</p> <p>Graham Moore writes the story in such a way that jolts you straight into the bustling 19th century Manhattan, and doesn’t let you go. The story captures depth in each of the historical figures with their own motives, obsessions, geniuses, and imperfections. It’s a complex fabric of many parallel threads involving rivalry, prestige, greed, obsession, egos, deception, resilience, love, growth, and many more themes. I wholeheartedly recommend this to both fiction- and non-fiction lovers!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="english"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="history"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ruthless legal battles against Thomas Edison in 19th century Manhattan]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">訴訟王エジソンの標的</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/last-days-of-night-jp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="訴訟王エジソンの標的"/><published>2022-10-25T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-25T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/last-days-of-night-jp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/last-days-of-night-jp/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/last-days-of-night-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/last-days-of-night-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/last-days-of-night-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/last-days-of-night.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <h3 id="読書の秋です">読書の秋です</h3> <p>もうすっかり秋も深まってきました。アメリカではカエデの木などが多い北東部が紅葉で有名ですが、私の住んでいる中西部もなかなか負けていないように感じます。もう今いる中西部に引っ越して5年以上（！）経ちますが、歳でしょうか笑、赤・黄・橙・茶と様々に色づく紅葉には、本当にうっとりと見惚れてしまいます。</p> <p>紅葉に加えて、秋といえば読書！ということで、私はいつもにも増していろんな本に手を出しています。過ごしやすい気温になってきた日中に陽の光の下で楽しむもよし、長くなってきた夜を読書で楽しむもよし、ですね。</p> <p>さて、今回はそんな中でも最近特に面白くて感銘を受けた一冊を。</p> <hr/> <h3 id="１９世紀末の電流戦争を鮮やかに描き出す歴史小説">１９世紀末の「電流戦争」を鮮やかに描き出す歴史小説</h3> <p>グレアム・ムーア著「訴訟王エジソンの標的」（英題は “The Last Days of Night”）は、事実をもとにした歴史小説。舞台は１９世紀末のニューヨーク・マンハッタンで、時代はまさに、それまで街を照らしてきたガス灯が電気照明へと移り変わろうとしている瞬間です。人々の中で、この新たな技術への興奮や不安が高まると同時に、街中の会社という会社が、なんとかこの新しい技術から一儲けしようとしのぎを削り合います。当時、磁石とコイルを使うと熱や光を発する「電流」なるものがあることは発見されていましたが、ほとんどの人は、電流が一体どういうメカニズムで生まれるのかさえ不明の状態で技術を利用しており、安全性への配慮の仕方もよくわかっていなかったため、感電事故や火事も頻発します。しかし、ガス灯の比ではない明るさで夜を照らし出す電気照明は、そんな不安をも押し殺すほど画期的であり、民衆を、そして事業家たちをどんどん虜にしていきます。</p> <p>この本のストーリーに登場するのは、ほぼ全て歴史上実在の人物ですが、今きっともっとも名前が知られているのはもちろん、トーマス・エジソン。エジソンは、電球を開発した天才発明家として有名ですが、「電球を本当に最初に発明したのは誰？」という問いへの答えは、一般に知られているほど明確ではないようです。１番有名となった特許を取ったのはエジソンでしたが、電流による発光はその何十年も前に実現していましたし、そもそも「電球」という今まで存在しない商品を作った場合、その「電球」というくくりでどこまでの商品がその特許でカバーされるのかは非常に不明瞭です。</p> <p>そんな時代を背景に「訴訟王エジソンの標的」では、電気照明にまつわる法廷闘争、技術闘争、そしてビジネス闘争が臨場感たっぷりに描かれます。闘争を繰り広げるのは、当時の電機会社二代巨頭、ウェスティングハウス・エレクトリックと、エジソンのゼネラル・エレクトリックで、この有名な争いは歴史上「電流戦争」と呼ばれているらしいです。</p> <p>グレアム・ムーアさんの語り口は、読み手を活気あふれる１９世紀末マンハッタンにぐっと引き込んで離しません。ただドラマチックに留まらず、それぞれの歴史上実在の登場人物に深みがあり、様々に異なる意図・目的・欲・才能・そして不完全生を抱えた存在として描かれているのも印象的でした。欲望をはらんだ駆け引き、絶望の中に生まれる希望、愛、成長など、面白いテーマがたくさん詰まった、最高のエンターテインメントを提供してくれました！</p> <p>それにしても、電気が一般化する前とあとで生活が大きく変わったことはぼんやりわかっていたけれど、電気が今まさにひかれようとしている瞬間というものが、いかに凄まじいものだったかというのは考えたことがなかったです。それがほんの少し味わえたような気持ちにさせてくれた本でした。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="japanese"/><category term="fiction"/><category term="history"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[１９世紀マンハッタンでの仁義なき法廷闘争]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Code Book</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/code-book-en/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Code Book"/><published>2022-10-10T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-10T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/code-book-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/code-book-en/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/codebook-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/codebook-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/codebook-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/codebook.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <h3 id="an-epic-tale-on-the-history-of-encryption">An epic tale on the history of encryption</h3> <p>Having felt so much joy from reading <em>Fermat’s Enigma</em>, I went straight to my next book by Simon Singh, <em>The Code Book</em>. This is a nonfiction book about the history of encryption. Honestly, my first take on this opening line was that it sounds a bit dry. I was familiar with the basic elements of modern encryption based on my work, and I couldn’t imagine how there could be so much to be told about it. Of course, I was dead wrong.</p> <p>Encryption basically refers to the process of ciphering text so that it cannot be read by anyone who the text is not intended for. Although many people today might associate the word “encryption” with computers, humans have been encrypting text for as long as we had civilizations. One of the classical form of encryption is called the “Caesar cipher”, and it gets its name from the famous Julius Caesar, a Roman general from 100 B.C.</p> <p>What <em>The Code Book</em> describes is the epic and very human tales of the continuous arms race between “codemakers”, who work to come up with secure forms of encryptions, and “codebreakers”, who try to find weaknesses in the state-of-the-art encryption system. These stories that are unraveled could not be farther from being dry. Perhaps it goes without saying that, any strong need to hide messages or to break someone’s hidden messages would almost always involve great historical tales.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="the-book-offers-great-technical-explanations">The book offers great technical explanations</h3> <p>The book is not only great in its storytelling, but also in its explanation of the technical method of enciphering and how the codebreakers got to deciphering each of them.</p> <p>One that I was particularly excited to learn about was the encryption and decryption of the German Enigma machine during WW2. This personally felt timely, since I had just watched <em>The Imitation Game</em>, a movie about Alan Turing’s contribution in breaking the Enigma, just a couple of months ago. The Enigma was by far the most difficult-to-break encryption in human history at the time, and I loved learning all the details of how it was made so unbreakable and how people went about breaking it. (Which were certainly details that the movie could not cover!)</p> <hr/> <h3 id="makes-me-appreciate-encryption-in-my-everyday-life">Makes me appreciate encryption in my everyday life</h3> <p>Throughout history, numerous methods of encryptions were invented, and each of them were deemed “unbreakable” at the time. However, each and every time, people have identified weaknesses in these means of encryption. The arms race involved numerous countries, countless wars, various fields of studies, and many, many brilliant minds. Our trusty modern-day encryption methods are the direct product of this very arms race. Now that I have become familiar with the faces and stories behind it, I have a renewed appreciation for it as I face my computer. This is exactly why I love learning history! It gives me an elevated appreciation of the world I live in :)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="english"/><category term="non-fiction"/><category term="history"/><category term="science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The history of ciphering text - from Julius Caesar to modern encryption]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">暗号解読</title><link href="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/code-book-jp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="暗号解読"/><published>2022-10-10T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-10T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/code-book-jp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sayadennis.github.io/blog/2022/code-book-jp/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/codebook-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/codebook-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/codebook-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/codebook.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/> <h3 id="暗号化の歴史壮絶な物語">暗号化の歴史、壮絶な物語</h3> <p>以前紹介したサイモン・シン著「フェルマーの最終定理」がおもしろすぎて、熱が冷めないうちにと思い、迷わず次に行きました。今回のサイモン・シン著「暗号解読」は、フェルマーの本の２年後に出版された本で、人類の暗号化の歴史について書かれたノンフィクション本です。実は私、最初にこの本について知ったとき、「暗号化の歴史」なんてちょっと味気なさそう、、、というのが第一印象でした。仕事柄、暗号化についての基本的な知識はあるつもりだったのですが、それが一体どうやったら本一冊書けるほど面白くなるのか、全く想像つかず。しかし蓋を開けてみると、一冊の本にも収まりきらないほど、溢れんばかりのおもしろストーリーが詰まっていました。</p> <p>暗号化、というとコンピューターを連想する人も多いかもしれませんが、実は、暗号化の歴史は、人類の文明の歴史と同じくらい古いものです。根本的なところでは、「暗号化」とは、「文字情報の秘匿化」とでも言いましょうか、文章の内容を他人にはわからないようにすることのことを指しています。もっとも歴史の古い暗号化の手法に「シーザー暗号」というものがありますが、この「シーザー」はかの有名な紀元前ローマの軍人、ユリウス・カエサルの名前であり、カエサルがこの暗号化を使ったことから命名されています。（「シーザー」は「カエサル」の英語読みです。スペルは”Caesar”）</p> <p>「暗号解読」に記されているのは、壮絶な、そして「味気なさそう」という第一印象に反して非常に人間的な、暗号の作り手（コードメーカー）と暗号解読者（コードブレーカー）の追いかけっこの歴史です。コードメーカーたちは常にその時代の最先端の、誰にも解読できない暗号を作り、コードブレーカーたちは、ときに趣味で、ときに政府の軍事作戦の一環として、誰にも解読できないとされた暗号を読み解いてきました。誰にも見られてはいけないメッセージ、そして本当は見てはいけないメッセージを見る必要性、、、そんな危なっかしい背景が伴う「暗号化」に面白い歴史のドラマが隠れているのは、よく考えてみたら当たり前のことかもしれないですね。</p> <hr/> <h3 id="暗号化の技術面の概要わかるところがさらに良い">暗号化の技術面の概要わかるところがさらに良い</h3> <p>私は人間大好き人間（？）なので、どんなお話でもヒューマンドラマに強く心惹かれるのですが、サイモン・シン著「暗号解読」の最高な点は、壮絶なヒューマンドラマに加えて、テクニカルな側面も十分に説明してくれているところ。時代の最先端の暗号化がどのような手法でされていたか、またその時代のコードブレーカーたちがどのようにしてその暗号を解読したのかが、当時最先端の数学・統計・機械学など「サイエンスの歴史」的な部分と交えて紹介されています。</p> <p>そんな中でも特に読んでいてテンションが上がったのは、第二次世界大戦で使われたドイツのエニグマ暗号の解読について。実はつい２〜３ヶ月前に、２０世紀の数学者アラン・チューリングのエニグマ解読についての映画「イミテーションゲーム」を観たばかりだったので、完全に個人的にタイムリーに感じられました笑。エニグマというのは、ドイツで作られた暗号化機械で、当時その暗号を解読することは何をどう頑張っても不可能とされていました。映画の中でもそんな話はされていたものの、「一体何をどうしたらそんなに難解な暗号ができたの！？」という好奇心にもちろん映画が応えてくれるはずもなく、、、しかしサイモン・シンはエニグマの内部をしっかりと図とともに解説してくれて、私の好奇心は大満足でした！</p> <hr/> <h3 id="毎日使う暗号化のありがたみを感じる">毎日使う暗号化のありがたみを感じる</h3> <p>人類の文明が始まってから今日に至るまで、様々な暗号化が開発されて、その都度「解読不可能」とみなされては、当時のコードブレーカーたちに弱みを見つけられ、解読されてきました。この「追いかけっこ」は、数々の国、戦争、様々な学問分野、そして数え切れないほどの天才たちから成る歴史です。私たちが今使っている暗号化は、この歴史の賜物以外のなにものでもありません。自分の目の前にあるツールの背景に潜む数々の「ひと」の姿を垣間見た今、そのありがたみが何倍にも増して感じられます。暗号化に限らず、歴史を学ぶことは、こういうありがたみに直結するなあと、いつも感じています。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="japanese"/><category term="non-fiction"/><category term="history"/><category term="science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[カエサルから近代コンピュータの暗号化まで、文字情報の秘匿化の歴史]]></summary></entry></feed>